PAUL JAY: Welcome back to The Real News Network.
This is Reality Asserts Itself, and I'm Paul
Jay.
We're continuing our series of interviews
with John Kiriakou, who joins us again in
the studio.
Thanks for joining us.
JOHN C. KIRIAKOU: Thanks for having me.
JAY: So, one more time, John's a former CIA
analyst and then became a caseworker. And
he's author of the book The Reluctant Spy:
My Secret Life in the CIA's War on Terror.
He spent about 23 months in jail and is now
under house arrest for another 40-odd days
for being the only person convicted of having
anything to do with the torture program in
the United States. And, no, he wasn't convicted
for torturing anybody; he was convicted for
whistleblowing.
Thanks for joining us.
KIRIAKOU: My pleasure.
JAY: How did you get recruited by the CIA?
KIRIAKOU: In grad school I took a class called
"Leadership", very simply. It was taught by
an eminent psychiatrist by the name of Dr.
Jerrold Post. Dr. Post is one of the country's
leading thinkers in the area of terrorist
psychology. So, in this class, one of our
assignments was to shadow our bosses and write
a psychological profile of that boss.
At the time, I was working at United Food
and Commercial Workers International Union
in Washington--long history of labor involvement
in my family. And I wrote a paper, and I said
that I believed my boss was a sociopath and
that he was potentially dangerous. And I offered
evidence to show why I thought he was potentially
dangerous.
So I got an A on this paper. And in the margin,
Dr. Post wrote, I've never done this before,
but I urge you to resign from this job. I
too believe that your boss is a sociopath.
So I quit and got another job.
In the meantime, he asked me to stay after
class one day, and he said, "Do you have any
job lined up after graduation?" And I said,
"Oh, Dr. Post, not only do I not have a job;
I don't even have any prospects for a job,
and I'm getting married a couple of weeks
after graduation." So he said, "Have you ever
given any thought to the CIA?" And I said,
"No, not really." "Do you think you'd be interested?"
I said, "Sure. I have nothing else going on."
And so he took me back to his office, went
through his Rolodex (in the days when everybody
had Rolodex). And as he was going through
the Rolodex, I remember seeing one card that
said, "Ollie North - Home", and it had a number.
And I thought, who is this guy that he has
Oliver North's home phone number in his Rolodex?
And this is pretty much in the midst of Iran-Contra.
We're just after the end of Iran-Contra. So
he calls a number and says, "Bob, are you
free? I have a good one," and hung up the
phone and said, "You need to go to Rosslyn,
the Rosslyn Metro station in Arlington, Virginia,
go to this address, and ask for Bob."
So I got on the subway, took it one stop to
Rosslyn. And I went to this completely nondescript
building that no longer exists and went up
to the sixth floor, and I buzzed a buzzer,
and a uniformed cop of some sort came out
and said, "Are you here for Bob?" I said,
"I am." So he lets me into a little atrium.
And there's another door that has a big spinlock
on it and a cipher, like a bank vault. So
he buzzes that door, and it opens, and a woman
pops her head out--just her head--and she
says, "Are you here for Bob?" I said, "I'm
here for Bob." So she lets me in.
And a minute later, this huge, six-foot-five,
350-pound guy comes out, and with his hand
out says, "Hi. I'm Bob. Are you John?" I said,
"I am." "Come on in here, John." And I talked
to him for a few minutes. And he said, "What
I want you to do is Saturday morning at 8
o'clock be at the George Washington University
medical center auditorium. You're going to
take some tests." I said okay.
So that Saturday morning, I went into town
and went to the medical school auditorium.
There were 200 people there at least. And
the proctors handed out these stacks of papers.
So one was a big map of the world, but it
was just blank. All the countries were divided,
but it was blank, and you had write in the
name of every country. And I say in my book,
I was always a map nut. So I just scribbled
in the names of all the countries. And the
next one was a current events test, multiple-choice.
Crazy easy. Like, you didn't even have to
subscribe to a newspaper at the time. If you
had just walked by the box holding The Washington
Post and looked at the top half of the front
page, you could have done well on this test.
It was very easy. I finished that quickly.
And then the first test was very long, several
thousand questions. The questions were all
yes or no.
And I also mention this in the book. As an
example, one of the questions was: I like
boxing. And the truth is, I didn't really
care one way or the other about boxing. Mike
Tyson was prominent at the time, and I liked
Mike Tyson. So I thought, well, I don't really
care about boxing, but if Mike Tyson's fighting,
I'll usually stop and watch it. So I put yes.
But then, like, 234 questions later, it says:
I like boxing. And I thought, geez, what did
I say the first time? I can't remember. I
think I said yes. I think. And I put yes.
And then another 400 questions later, it says:
I like boxing. And I was like, geez, oh man.
So you see what they're doing. They're looking
for patterns.
So I did it. I finished it. I finished it
first of anybody. And I sat there for a while
and looked around, and nobody else was getting
up, so I thought, ah, I'm done. So I got up,
I handed it to the proctor, and I walked out.
My wife picks me up and she says, how'd you
do? I said, I have no idea, I have no idea
how I did. I said, the questions were so weird,
I'm not sure what they were looking for. A
week or so later, I get a call from Bob. He
says, you blew the doors off that test. I
want you to go to another equally nondescript
building in Vienna, Virginia, and take some
more tests.
PAUL JAY, SENIOR EDITOR, TRNN: Were any of
the questions on the test political? What
do you think of this, what do you think of
that?
KIRIAKOU: No, nothing like that.
JAY: It's all attitudinal.
KIRIAKOU: All attitudinal.
The current events test was so simple it was--I
remember one of the questions was the Prime
Minister of Greece is (a) Andreas Papandreou,
(b) Mao Zedong, (c) Leonid Brezhnev, or (d)
U Thant. So, come on. You know, I just blew
right through it.
JAY: When you're thinking about joining the
CIA, first of all, it doesn't sound like you
thought too much about it.
KIRIAKOU: I didn't think at all about it.
JAY: But did it not occur to you to think
about the Church committee, for example, that--you
must have been aware (you're a savvy guy)
that--
KIRIAKOU: Oh, yeah. I had--.
JAY: --the Church committee--. But let me
just--
KIRIAKOU: Sorry.
JAY: --well, just for people that don't know,
I mean, the Church committee that investigated
terrible misdeeds--assassination attempts--so,
I mean, terrible, terrible things that the
Church committee revealed. And afterwards,
there are many investigative pieces in newspapers
and magazines, and the CIA had done bad stuff.
KIRIAKOU: Bad stuff.
JAY: That didn't ring for you, do I want to
be a part of this?
KIRIAKOU: I knew a guy in college whose father
worked at the CIA, and I asked him if he would
have coffee with me one day. And I asked him
questions.
And then there was a woman I knew in grad
school whose boyfriend worked at the CIA.
And I did the same thing with him. We had
dinner one night. And they told me that, yes,
the Church committee had revealed terrible
crimes, but by God, the CIA had cleaned up
its act, and it's a great place to work, and
you're going to love it, because everything
is good and everything's clean now and everything's
by the book. And I said, great, that sounds
like a place for me.
JAY: And who can say no to Bob?
KIRIAKOU: That's right. Who could say no to
Bob?
JAY: Alright. So you go to another nondescript
building. And another Bob?
KIRIAKOU: No. I'm met there by three individuals:
a psychologist, a psychiatrist, and an anthropologist.
And they interview me. And they're asking
me questions like, describe your relationship
with your mother. And I said, well, I have
a terrific mother. You know, she's always
been supportive. We've always gotten along.
And they look at each other and nod. Describe
your relationship with your father. Was your
father the disciplinarian in the family?
And then, finally, they ask me a question
that still sticks with me: have you ever betrayed
a friendship? And I said, oh my God, I hope
not. I don't think so. I said, let me think
about it. They said, no, no, that's the answer
we were looking for. I said, okay. When that
was done, they took hair, blood, urine, sent
me on my way. And then, a week later, Bob
calls and says, you aced those tests, so we're
going to send you for interviews. So he set
up a day's worth of interviews at CIA headquarters.
And a couple of weeks after that, I got an
offer in the mail.
JAY: Now, you wrote in your book, I believe,
that they like to look for people--did you
call trending towards sociopath?
KIRIAKOU: Well, a CIA psychiatrist told me
one time that the CIA looks to hire people
with sociopathic tendencies--not sociopaths,
because sociopaths have no consciences. But
people with sociopathic tendencies are comfortable
operating in moral and legal gray areas.
JAY: So do you think they found that in you?
KIRIAKOU: I think they probably did, because
at that time, when they asked me the question--they
offered a scenario. They said, you know that
Mr. X has something in his house that you
need, whether it's a file or whatever. You
need it. And you work on him to recruit him
so that eventually he turns that file over
to you. But he's not recruitable. And in the
end, when you ask him for the file, he tells
you, no. What do you do? I said, I break into
the house and take the file. Seemed like a
perfectly logical answer to me.
JAY: 'Cause they were--but you understood
they were asking you--
KIRIAKOU: Oh, of course.
JAY: --to think like a CIA person.
KIRIAKOU: Absolutely.
JAY: I mean, did you believe that? Or you
were feeding them something you thought they
wanted to hear?
KIRIAKOU: No, I believed that. If Mr. X was
a Russian scientist, let's say, I would absolutely
break into his house and take it. Right? We're
the good guys. They're the bad guys.
JAY: Right.
KIRIAKOU: So, sure, I believed it.
JAY: So you're hired. You go through orientation.
And you write in the book that one of the
people that's giving you the orientation--I'm
quoting--made the biggest impression. The
director of the Office of Security made the
biggest impression on you, saying something
that stayed with you all these years, that,
he said, the greatest threat facing America
today is the threat of Soviet communism. And
you didn't think so.
KIRIAKOU: I thought that was absurd. This
is January 1990, right? The Berlin wall's
down, the Soviet Union is breaking up, and
Eastern Europe is turning democratic, and
this old man is standing there telling us
that the greatest threat we face is Soviet
communism? I thought it was ridiculous. And
I wondered if it was just for show, if it
was to make us feel like, wow, we're really
part of something now. But as the years passed,
I think I've come to the conclusion that he
believed it, that he was one of those old
timers who just couldn't change with the times.
JAY: Just the culture was too embedded. What
did you think was the greatest threat? And
were you joining because you thought there
was a threat? Or you were joining 'cause it's
something interesting to do?
KIRIAKOU: No, I thought it would be interesting.
And, frankly, I was looking forward to the
travel. That's really what was most exciting
for me.
You know, I really didn't think there was
any large transnational threat at the time,
except maybe terrorism. And I had my own thoughts
on terrorism. I believed that the real threat
was nationalist terrorism or communist terrorism,
whether it was PFLP, DFLP, PFLP-GC, some of
the Greek groups, the Red Brigades, the Action
directe. You know, those were the groups that
were killing Americans overseas. Hezbollah--although
that was religious and not nationalist. That's
where I thought the real threats were coming,
not the former Soviet Union. And that's what
it was at that point: it was already the former
Soviet Union.
JAY: Right. So you get in and very quickly
you're sent to Kuwait?
KIRIAKOU: Well, I was given Kuwait as what
they called a training account. I was told,
you know, Kuwait has this very interesting
democratic movement. People demonstrate every
once in a while. They're experimenting with
a democratically elected parliament. So learn
Kuwait, learn how to write in the CIA's analytic
style, and then you can move on to something
really interesting, like Romania. That's what
the guy told me. So I thought, doggone it,
I'm going to be stuck with this country where
nothing ever happens; I'm never going to get
promoted.
JAY: This is still based--you're still in
Arlington? Or you're actually in Kuwait?
KIRIAKOU: No, I'm in Arlington, still.
JAY: Yeah.
KIRIAKOU: So I did Kuwait for four months.
And then, in April 1990, I also picked up
Iraq. And at the time, in the CIA, you could
count on two hands the number of people that
covered Iraq. And I mean in everything--analysis,
operations. Everything. Press. You name it.
Again, I was told that Iraq is a good training
company. Nothing ever changes there. It's
the same cabinet since 1968, right? No changes,
nothing happens, no trouble, no problems.
I said, okay.
JAY: Now, just to be clear for everybody,
you're in the analysis section, not the operations
section.
KIRIAKOU: No. We had very poor relations with
Iraq at the time, so our embassy was very,
very small. It was something like four or
five people. There wasn't really much reporting
coming out of it. I'd read the Iraqi papers
every day or translations of the Iraqi papers
that weren't in English. And I was really
more focused on [Kuwait].
And then, on August 2, 1990, Iraq invaded
Kuwait--I should say I was more focused on
Kuwait. So Iraq invaded Kuwait. The night
before the invasion, we predicted that the
Iraqis would of course cross the border.
And I had a softball game that night. The
CIA has its own softball league. That way,
if you say something classified, it's okay,
because everybody's a CIA employee. Right?
So I had a softball game that night. And one
of the older guys came up to me and said,
I don't think you understand how important
this Iraq-Kuwait thing is. He said, it's one
thing for our country to go to war with another
country. Let me rephrase that. It's one thing
for our countries to go to war with each other,
the countries that we cover. It's an entirely
different thing for the country we cover to
go to war with us. He said, you have a chance
here to really become somebody. So pay close
attention and do your analysis.
JAY: And how much pressure was there on you,
next-Iraq-war style, to shape and modify your
analysis in favor of Saddam's totally the
bad guy, our hands are clean?
KIRIAKOU: Yeah, you mean in 2003?
JAY: No, no, no. I'm talking back this. When
you're analyzing--like, for example--.
KIRIAKOU: In 1990?
JAY: Yeah, prior to the first Gulf War. It
later came out how much bullshit there was,
like this infant that was supposedly--infants
being tortured story was apparently a fraud.
There's pretty good documentation the American
ambassador to Iraq lets Saddam know--.
KIRIAKOU: No, that's not true. I was there
that night. She got a bum rap on that. That
was Ambassador April Glaspie.
JAY: Right.
KIRIAKOU: April Glaspie was instructed by
the secretary of state, who was James Baker
at the time, to go to see Saddam and to tell
Saddam that the United States will not take
a position on Arab-Arab border disputes. That's
all she said.
JAY: No, don't think it's ever--any more than
that's ever been said that she said. The interpretation's
been that we will not intervene.
KIRIAKOU: Well, after the fact, the press
said that Saddam's interpretation was that
that was a green light. But her instructions
were not to give him the green light.
JAY: I understand. As I've always heard the
story, what you said is what she said.
KIRIAKOU: Yeah.
JAY: But there was never a suggestion that
we would intervene. Quite the opposite: this
is your business between you and Kuwait, and
we're going to stay out of it. That was the--.
KIRIAKOU: Nobody, nobody expected him to take
the entire country. Frankly, we expected that
Iraqi troops would move across the border
and that they would take that narrow strip
on the Kuwaiti side that included the southern
tip of the Rumaila oil field. That's what
everybody expected to happen, 'cause, frankly,
the truth of the matter is that Kuwaitis were
drilling horizontally. So they were drilling
in their little tip of the Rumaila oil field
underneath the Iraqi border and they were
stealing the oil.
JAY: Stealing Iraqi oil.
KIRIAKOU: Stealing Iraqi oil.
JAY: And you knew that at the time.
KIRIAKOU: Everybody did, and it was in the
papers and everything. So everybody, including
us, believed that the Iraqis would move across
the border, take the oilfield, and that would
be the end of it. In fact, within 24 hours
they took the entire country and then just
began murdering everybody.
JAY: But some of the murder stories were exaggerated.
This murder of infants stuff didn't happen.
KIRIAKOU: Yeah, I never understood why the
Kuwaitis felt compelled to exaggerate those
stories, because there were so many despicable
crimes against humanity that Iraqi soldiers
were committing in Kuwait. There was no reason
to lie about them. I remember when the girl
that you're speaking about testified before
Congress. I remember watching that at the
CIA and saying, I know that girl. Isn't she
the Kuwaiti ambassador's daughter? That's
Saud Nasser's daughter.
JAY: Right.
KIRIAKOU: So, I mean, it only took about a
day or two to break the story that this whole
thing was a setup.
JAY: Right.
KIRIAKOU: And, frankly, the Kuwaitis were
guilty of lying and trying to propagandize
the situation. But so was their public relations
firm. I don't think the Kuwaitis came up with
that on their own.
JAY: And when you say everyone expected it
to come in and just take the oilfield, then
it's not that much of a stretch for Saddam
to say, well, I have a green light to take
the oilfield.
KIRIAKOU: At the time, I would have said that
that was insane. I can see how he may have
believed that he had a green light. But Ambassador
Glaspie certainly did not believe she was
giving him a green light.
JAY: 'Cause the overall suggestion is that
U.S. policymakers wanted Saddam to go--give
him some rope to hang himself, because they
wanted an excuse to have the first war.
KIRIAKOU: I never believed that, because Saddam
was the only thing that we had standing between
Iran and the small Gulf countries. We needed
Saddam and the Iranians to just kill each
other for decades.
JAY: Well, that's the same argument made about
the next Saddam war, except that didn't stop
the invasion.
KIRIAKOU: Right.
JAY: So one can wonder.
KIRIAKOU: Yeah. Well, that just goes to show
you what a stupid policy we had in 2003, to
provoke this war with the Iraqis, because
now we've created a regional hegemon in Iran.
We took out an entire sect of Iraq, and we've
disenfranchised Sunnis, we've taken their
positions, we've taken them out of government
and out of the military, and you have an entirely
Shia military in Iraq now that is in some
ways supportive of Iran's theocracy and in
other ways accepting of it.
JAY: We're going to carry on with your story
from Kuwait further in the next segment of
our interview.
Please join us for the continuation of Reality
Asserts Itself with John Kiriakou on The Real
News Network.